<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>ANNIS Developer Guide</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
                <surname>Krause</surname>
            </personname>
            <email>annis-admin@ling.uni-potsdam.de</email>
        </author>
        <orgname>SFB 632 Information Structure / D1 Linguistic Database</orgname>
        <orgname>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin &amp; Universität Potsdam</orgname>
        <releaseinfo>Version ${project.version}</releaseinfo>
        <pubdate>${mavenBuildTimestamp}</pubdate>

    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Building ANNIS</title>
        <para>ANNIS uses <link xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven3</link> as build tool.
        Maven itself is based on Java and should run on every major operating system.
        You have to download and install the appropriate version for your operating system from 
            <link xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</link>
        before you can build ANNIS. Maven will download all needed dependencies from central servers
        on the first build so you will need to have a working internet connection. The dependencies
        are cached locally once their are downloaded.
        </para>
        <para> When you have downloaded or checked out the source of ANNIS the top-level directory
            of the source code is the parent project for all ANNIS sub-projects. If you want to
            build every project that is part of ANNIS just execute
            <programlisting>cd &lt;annis-sources>/
mvn install            </programlisting> This
            might take a while on the first execution. <code>mvn clean</code> will remove all
            compiled code if necessary. </para>
        <para>If you only want to compile a sub-project execute <code>mvn install</code> in the
            corresponding sub-directory. Every folder with a sub-project will have a
                <filename>pom.xml</filename> file. These files configure the whole build process.
            The Maven documenation contains detailed explanations of the structure and possible
            content of the configuration files.</para>
        <para> Some sub-projects don't provide a library but will produce a zip or tar/gz-file when
            they are compiled. These assembly steps (see <link
                xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-assembly-plugin/">Maven
                documentation</link>) are automatically invoked on <code>mvn install</code>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Using an IDE</title>
        <para>While you can use any text editor of your choice to change ANNIS and compile it
            completly on the command line using Maven, a proper IDE will be a huge help for you.
            You can use any IDE which has a good support for Maven. The ANNIS main developers
            currently recommend the Netbeans 7.x IDE for development.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Frontend</title>
        <para>The ANNIS frontend is a web application implemented in Java and the <link
                xlink:href="https://vaadin.com/">Vaadin</link> framework. It communicates 
            with the backend service via a REST interface.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Running an embedded Jetty instance for local access</title>
            <para> This way of running the frontend is very useful, if you want to access Annis on
                you local machine as a single user. </para>
            <para> You don't need to install Jetty or Tomcat by yourself using this method. A
                security manager has to be configured. The recommend (and most easy to configure)
                security manager for this setup is the TestSecurityManager.
                <programlisting>cd &lt;unzipped source>/annis-gui/
mvn jetty:run</programlisting>
                Now you can access the site under <link
                    xlink:href="http://localhost:8080/annis-gui/app"
                    >http://localhost:8080/annis-gui/app</link>. The Jetty server might be stopped
                by pressing "CTRL-C". </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>HOWTO add new visualizers</title>
            <para>TODO</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</article>
